so common practice that I hear about is
like
this a person wants to practice
equinity wants to have this it sounds
quite nice
equinity not being bothered by things
always peaceful but but it is because
they are not peaceful they are bothered
right so so it's like well I can practice
so so it's like well I can practice
these four Brahma viharas basically you
know meta and so on so sometimes I do
meta sometimes I do karuna sometimes
ubca sometimes
mudita depends on how I feel or what's
uh attractive at the moment yeah so cuz
I can't just do matter all the time it's
a bit boring but so equinity is quite a
nice one and
uh and they they go about like this so I
feel bothered by
somebody and then I go away and I sit by
myself and I
do this Equanimity practice by imagining
this person the situation and just
trying to invoke a sense an energy of
equinity of of just like I'm okay with this
of of just like I'm okay with this
person who's irritating me I'm okay with
a situation that's
absolutely you know making me so
angry so they just and then just kind of
trying to
push this economist
feeling into them into that Minds into
the perception of
that is there something wrong with that
or can the person just keep on doing
that hard you know well there a few
things wrong with it um the two main
points two main mistakes are well first
of
all it's not that you're not equanimous
because you haven't practiced Brahma
viharas you're not equanimous because
you're still liable to be disturbed in
other words you don't know how to remain
unaffected even before you were
Disturbed the mind is not developed so
you have no choice but to experience the
Disturbed mind when something agitates
it and disturbs it you don't know how to
prevent that so the only thing you know
is how to then cover it up or try to try
to reshape it or or or whatever practice
you might be doing basically the only
way you know is to uh try to deal with
it and that's a problem see the issue is
not that you have not found a perfect
way of dealing with it you might well
have found an excellent way of dealing
with it but that was never the problem
the problem was that you were affected
in the first place as I keep
saying and the true Equanimity is when
you can't be affected in the first place
then what is there to deal with that's
the true peace I don't need to do
anything on account of this because I'm
not bothered I am peaceful if I have to
do this if I have to do bramara if I
have to do that if I have to do Sam if I
have to do any practices because I'm
bothered means that's not Equanimity
even if I calm myself down with these
practices so that's the first problem
really and kind of the the the
fundamental one
uh so then really you want to ask
yourself like uh why am I Disturbed in
the first place why can I be disturbed
in the first place cuz you obviously
don't want to disturbance
yet you can't help it when you
experience something
that's challenging annoying
unpleasant the mind just gets
Disturbed so what do you learn from that
you learn that your own mind doesn't
listen to you you want it to not get
Disturbed you want it to remain peaceful
but it ignores you it just goes and does
it
anyway and then you try to paste the
practices over that's your second
problem so you you don't you don't see
what happened there that already so that
was the issue the issue was not even
that you were
Disturbed the issue was that your own
mind is not listening to you so sooner
or later something will highlight that
something will make that apparent to you
and that's where you Disturbed that's
when you are not equanimous so instead
of looking at at the root of that and
what causes the mind to not listen to
you you just want to cover up the fact
that mine doesn't listen to you that
it's causing you pain and now I just
want to cover up the pain with a with a
like a shoving the the the the the
square shape into a circle like do your
Brahma viharas do Equanimity do meta
just so that this pain goes away on
account of the mind that doesn't listen
to me and that will continue not
listening to me because I'm not doing
anything on that field
so also what's
uh it's not that you you're not saying
that Brahma vihara is wrong no I'm I'm
saying that interpretation completely
yeah yeah so Brahma vihara is the actual
practice of taming your mind so it's in
the complete opposite direction of how
people do it so in order to T in order
to develop Brahma Viara first you need
to see your own mind as that thing that
you are paired with that doesn't listen
to you that needs taming that needs
containment and develop Clarity in
regard to that then that can take you in
the dire direction of actual Brahma
viharas so it's not something you have
to be like doing it you could just be
amplifying these aspects of taming the
mind that then result in Brahma viharas
certain Frameworks so unless you have a
right view unless you have seen the
signs of your mind I seen this mind as a
phenomenon see the mind as as that thing
that needs
taming unless you have developed a
degree of kind of un identification with
your own mind any basically practice of
Brahma vihara you do is just a practice
of your wrong view on the pretext of
Brahma viharas that's not what Brahma
viharas are I mean imagine it's the dwelling of
are I mean imagine it's the dwelling of
the
brahmas it takes a bit more to dwell
like a Brahma than to just have positive
thoughts about your fellow men which
anybody can do and you don't need a
Buddha to teach you that he takes a bit
more effort he takes a bit more of
commitment endurance and mental kind of
elevation basically takes more depth and that
basically takes more depth and that
depth begins with the Right View so the
right view in this case is found in the
direction of recognizing hold
on I have a meditation technique I do
Brahma viharas I go on the Retreats and
it really helps my life I'm much calmer
person but do I actually know how how to do
but do I actually know how how to do
have confidence in the knowledge
of being undisturbed to begin with or do
I just have confidence that sooner or
later I will get my retreat I will do my
technique and I will calm
down which one is
it do I know how factually to remain
undisturbed in face of disturbances do I
have confidence that this wild mind of
mine will not turn against me because
I've tamed it
because I know how to speak to it I see
it signs and features and I prevent it
from going into the wrong
pastures or I have absolutely no idea
what any of that means and I just sort
of calm myself through focusing
practices so that's the beginning
basically that's your your your
Crossroads to to realize you can't be
practicing both you can't be going in
the direction of digging up the reasons
that your mind doesn't listen to you
restraining them purifying them and at
the same time engaging in avoiding pain
that the mind that the wild mind causes
you through through focusing and through
calming and so
on they're mutually
exclusive because each time you act out
of avoiding pain that that wild mind
caus you you're feeding its wildness
you're feeding its
Disobedience you're just trying to deal
with the pain of it ignoring the fact
that pain was really not the problem the
problem was the mind that has the
ability and power to turn against you
and you can't stop it you can't do
anything about it and and you can
actually see that even in like U
day-to-day examples of your life not
even necessarily some extreme scenarios
where the Mind turns against you you
could just see that like sometimes for
example one thing happens to you and
you're not
bothered the mind doesn't really L on it
doesn't pick on it does not start
nagging you and causing you that mental
turmoil on another occasion something
much smaller than that happens yet
because of this or that the mind won't
let go of it and you can't sleep at
night and you filled with whatever it
might be anger any form of hindrance
anything because this mind just won't
let go of it and you would want to let
go of it you would want to be peaceful
but if you measure your peace whether
it's the pain I'm feeling or the
pleasure you're ignoring that that was
never the problem that's the result of
the problem problem of an untamed
mind so if you have Untamed mind and
then try to pce Brahma viharas or any
other Buddhist practice like without
developing the right view in terms of
taming the Mind none none of that will
work and that all of that will become a
misrepresentation of the
dhama so you think you're practicing the
dhama while you're
not and would that's that's somebody you
used to you've mentioned before it's
like uh I don't know if I'm getting
right but it's like if you got a
cancer and because of that cancer you
have a headache and so you take a
tablet yeah and it gets rid of the pain
yeah of you know you think you're King
cancer but all yeah you're just kind of
numbing the pain for a while exactly and
but if I keep on if I keep on taking a
headache tablet canc will dis the Brahma
vihara practice of wishing everyone well
then I won't get Angry Anymore yeah
that's kind of exactly exactly the the
implicit implication by like most people
engaging these practices is that I know
it's not adequate but there is this kind
of concealed hope in it that if I just
keep covering my pain long enough one
day it just won't be there
anymore so if I keep taking the pills
and never allow headache to come up one
day I'll be cancer
free and it's like that doesn't work
even in in mundane terms and you know it
let alone when it comes to freeing your
mind and and reaching Nana
yeah you want to M
yeah so if sometimes symptoms are too
much yes take the headache pill Cal down
but don't confuse that for treating the
illness which is not having headache in
the first place on account of your
mental cancer and in this case being mind that
cancer and in this case being mind that
can turn against
you at its whim if something prompts it
if circumstances change if
if you didn't get enough sleep not
enough food or something that that mind
becomes agitated and and and and sort of
um touchy and it turns against you and
it starts causing you trouble basically
your own thinking is not in your control
it starts annoying you harassing you
bombarding you with stuff causing you
pain disturbing you and you can't stop
it and you will never stop it for as
long as you don't start um basically
admitting that that's really the root of
the problem regardless of what pain
might come out of it so don't be just
trying to act out of I just want to get
rid of the pain no no no put the
symptoms aside for a while so that you
can discern the
illness in this case illness is yeah
it's my own mind simply not listening to
my
commands and why is that well cuz you
never trained it I mean you just take a
random street dog and start telling it
to sit it's not going to do it but it's
not impossible to teach it either but
you do have to make the effort so you
have to recognize okay that's the
training that's talking about the
training the dog training of your own
mind and Once the mind is
trained as the suit is often described
like Arun is like an unmovable Mountain
regardless of the weather that's hitting
it and and falling and the rain and the
wind so no amount of circumstances will
make a trained mind turn against
itself so in other words no amount of
circumstances will make you suffer
irrationally and if it's turning against
itself it's not it's not trained enough
or it's not trained at all depending on
how badly it stands against itself yeah
so you want to find out how to train the
mind well listen to our other 200 and
plus something talks which is all about
again seeing where the problem is
containing your
behavior curbing your UNH wholesome sort
of Engagement with sense objects sense
restraint obviously reading the sutas
and learning more but be careful with
that as we said before like you can be
reading the sutas and all of that just
to get rid of the pain of your headaches
it's like no no no all of that is to
inform you how to keep getting closer to
the illness to the cancer of your mind
not to treat you with pain right away
that's why the Buddha described that for
somebody practice towards Enlightenment
is going to be slow and painful
throughout but if he has the right view
he'll see past that
pain he won't measure the successes
whether whether it's painful or not
he'll measure whether the mind is
getting more obedient or not for
somebody if the mind was not as wild
pleasure uh practice can be very
pleasant very agreeable but again it's
still the same training by the way
because sometimes even this is something
people like oh yeah I need to have this
pleasure and joy because the Buddha said
practice is joyful well that's not up to
you to decide that's up to that dog you
picked up off the street to decide
whether that dog is intelligent enough
capable enough whether he can pick the
command quickly so it's up to your
mind if it's a complete wreck
unrestrained for years it's not going to
be enjoyable enjoyable but it's still
the same training and it will still have
the same results if you do it and that's
the
point so as as somebody said there is a
difference between chaining your mind
and actually taming it like chain a dog
and actually train it so the same
applies to the mind and the reason for
that is exactly like you can be just
imposing all the all the precepts all
the sense restraint like controlling
your environment constricting it so
there is nothing disturbing coming your
way and then confuse that for training
the mind for taming it in the same sense
you could just get a wild dog and train
it but if you don't train it in any way
if you don't learn how to communicate to
it with it it will still bite bite you
if you come within its
range so in this case again yes first
you have to chain it if the mind is just
even if that dog is completely wild well
you're certainly not going to train it
if he can come and go as it pleases and
the Buddha gave the simul in regards to
the elephant but it was exactly the same
thing yeah you find first you have to
just tie it down with the leather
straps where it can't go as it pleases
and but then you realize that's the
beginning so keeping the precepts and
containing myself putting the chain on
my own mind it's the beginning now and
when I see that it's becoming like
calmer because of that okay then I have
to learn how to now discern its
inclinations and engage it with opposing
ones like if he wants to Incline toward
sensuality well I'll present it with
dangers and perils and dissatisfaction
and all the termal I had to go through
account of getting what I wanted and
I'll I'll feed it that not I'll beat it
until it turns
away because that's just trying to get
rid of your own thoughts as we say which
is again rooted in craving and ill will
and in other words you're just making
your mind even
Wilder no just presented this context
and protect the contexts of peril the
danger the lack of satisfaction the the
all the simul the Buddha gave about
sensuality until that mind sort of
admits yeah okay see you taught it a
lesson then wants to go
towards self-loading oh this is none of this is
self-loading oh this is none of this is
wor all this well be that as it may
there is factual Liberation from all of
it there is a factual ease there is a
factual nibana there is a factual
peace present it with that context when
it gets too dark there is factual
benefits of even this limited training
you did there is the again there is like
the the the the simple
immovability or the increased
immovability of your mind that comes
just with with keeping the precepts like
mind becomes much more stable less prone
to be irrational emotional and you see
that and you know that deep down it's
just that when the mind gets a bit
darker you forget that and then you let
it wallow so again you don't beat it to
stop you just present it with a context
but look if you don't go too far that
way you could develop this equilibrium
you could develop this immeasurable
pleasure of Peace which is what you
always wanted and that's how you train
it when it goes when it's too tight you
loosen it when it's too loose you
tighten it but the work has to be done
how painful that training will be well
depends on how patient you are how Wild
the mind was and and many different
factors and that's really as I said
before that's not the point the point is
to go through the training procedure